<chapter>
<title>Bundled Programs</title>
<para>
Several binaries and curve parameters are bundled with the PBC library,
such as the <command>pbc</command> program
that was discussed in an earlier chapter.
</para>
<para>
The <filename>param</filename>
subdirectory contains pairing parameters one might use in
a real cryptosystem. Many of the test programs read the parameters
from files such as these on standard input, for example:
</para>
<screen>benchmark/benchmark &lt; param/c159.param
example/bls &lt; param/e.param
</screen>
<section>
<title>Parameter Generation</title>
<para>
Programs that generate pairing parameters are located in the
<filename>gen</filename> subdirectory. Some of the programs are already
functional enough to be used to find parameters for real applications.
I need to write more documentation first; for now, read
the source!
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>listmnt</term>
<listitem><para>
Searches for discriminants D that lead to MNT curves with subgroups
of prime order.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>genaparam</term>
<term>gena1param</term>
<term>gendparam</term>
<term>geneparam</term>
<term>genfparam</term>
<listitem><para>
Prints parameters for a curve suitable for computing pairings of a given
type. The output can be fed to some of the other test programs.
</para>
<para>
The program <command>gendparam</command>
should be given a discriminant as the first argument.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>hilbertpoly</term>
<listitem><para>
Prints the Hilbert polynomial for a given discriminant (the first argument).
Computing the Hilbert polynomial is an intermediate step when generating
type D parameters.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>
<section>
<title>Example Cryptosystems</title>
<para>
In the <filename>example</filename> subdirectory there are various programs
that read curve parameters on standard input and perform computations
that would be required in a typical implementation of a pairing-based
cryptosystem.
</para>
<para>
Of course, more work would be required to turn these programs
into real applications. The main purpose is to showcase the PBC library
API.
</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Benchmarks</title>
<para>
I use the programs in the <filename>benchmark</filename> subdirectory
to measure running times of pairings, and also RSA decryptions.
</para>
<para>
The <command>benchmark</command> program takes
pairing parameters on standard input and reports the average running
time of the pairing over 10 runs, while <command>timersa</command>
reports the time required to perform one 1024-bit RSA decryption.
</para>
</section>
</chapter>
